A Finding Aid to the Gary Falk Papers, circa 1955-2013, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Gary Falk papers
circa 1955-2013
Archives of American Art
Falk, Gary M., 1954-1986
AAA.falkgary
Archival Resource Key
2.5 Linear feet
0.005 Gigabytes
The papers of painter and assemblage artist Gary Falk measure 2.5 linear feet and 0.005 GB and date from circa 1955-2013. The papers document his career as an artist in New York through biographical material, including project proposals, student records, and items from his memorial service; a small amount of personal correspondence; four notebooks; exhibition files; printed material; photographs of Falk, Falk with friends, artwork, and travel; digital photographs of artwork; and original artwork, including drawings, collages, and two sketchbooks.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated 2005, 2007, 2014, and 2016 by Lillian Falk, Gary Falk's mother.
Related Materials
Also at the Archives of American Art is one sound recording of Ned Rifkin in conversation with Gary Falk, December 5, 1984.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter and assemblage artist Gary Falk measure 2.5 linear feet and 0.005 GB and date from circa 1955-2013. The papers document his career as an artist in New York through biographical material, including project proposals, student records, and items from his memorial service; a small amount of personal correspondence; four notebooks; exhibition files; printed material; photographs of Falk, Falk with friends, artwork, and travel; digital photographs of artwork; and original artwork, including drawings, collages, and two sketchbooks.
Biographical / Historical
Gary Falk (1954-1986) was a painter and assemblage artist from New York, N.Y. Falk developed a personal sign system in his works of art, and often worked in enamel and acrylic on Plexiglas or aluminum.
Falk and his family moved to Bethesda, Maryland, in 1966. He attended the Corcoran School of Art and later graduated from Yale University with a degree in Fine Arts in 1975. After college he moved to New York City and worked as an artist. He had a one-man-show at the New Museum of Contemporary Art in 1983. During the 1980s, he participated in many other group exhibitions, most notably Narrative Forms (1984) at the Museo Rufino Tamayo and SIGNS (1985) at the New Museum. Falk died at the age of 32.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as 7 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1966-2013 (0.5 Linear feet; Box 1, 0.005 GB; ER01)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1973-1996 (4 Folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Notebooks, 1979-circa 2004 (4 Folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 1977-1988 (0.3 Linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1962-1990 (0.2 Linear feet; Box 2, OV 5)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1955-1990s (0.7 Linear feet; Boxes 2-4)
Series 7: Artwork, 1958-1980s (0.5 Linear feet; Box 3, OVs 5-7)
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs; Art -- Study and teaching; Assemblage artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Drawings; Sketchbooks; Collages
- Biographical Material, circa 1966-2013; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1; 0.005 Gigabytes ER01
  Scope and Contents
  Found here are Gary Falk's appointment books, passport, and wallet, as well as lists and digital photographs of his works, project proposals, and records of his time as a student at Yale University. Also found are a short memoir written by Lillian Falk, Gary's mother, and items from his memorial service, including eulogies, and recordings of the speakers and music on two sound cassettes.
  - Birth Certificate (Copy), circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appointment Book Pages, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appointment Book, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Appointment Book, 1983-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Donation to FHI 360 Art Collection, 2013; Archival Resource Key; 1 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lists and Images of Works in Collections, 1999; 2013; 2004; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER01 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Images of Works in Collections, Digital Photographs, 2006; Archival Resource Key; 0.005 Gigabytes 72 computer files (Folder ER01)
  - List of Large Scale Public Projects, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memoir by Lillian Falk, 2006-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memorial Service, 1986; Archival Resource Key; Includes 2 sound cassettes. (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Material, circa 1970s-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Passport, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Project Proposals, 1980-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rolodex Pages, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Wallet, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Yale University Student Records, 1973-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1973-1996; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1
  The small amount of correspondence found here includes a personal letters to Gary Falk, and a few postcards he sent his parents. Also found are letters of condolence and letters to his parents regarding the posthumous exhibition of his artwork.
  - Letters to Gary Falk, 1980-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gary Falk Postcards to Parents, 1973; 1982-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letters and Condolences to Lillian and Charles Falk, 1986-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
- Notebooks, 1979-circa 2004; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1
  Notebooks from 1979 and 1985 contain general notes, including some sales records and project ideas. One travel notebook documents a trip to Italy. One notebook from circa 2004 only contains a few entries and possibly belonged to Gary Falk's parents.
  - Notebook, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notebook, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Travel Notebook, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Notebook, circa 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Exhibition Files, 1977-1988; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Found here are files documenting exhibitions in which Gary Falk showed works. The contents of each file varies, but may include exhibition catalogs and announcements, press clippings, photographs, correspondence, loan agreements, and price lists.
  - Sarah Lawrence College, Painting 75 76 77 (1977), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Fashion Institute of Technology, Dianne B. Collection Autumn 1981, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - New Museum, The Window (1983), 1982-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - University of Texas at Austin, New American Painting: A Tribute to James and Mari Michener (1984), 1983-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Bette Stoler Gallery, Art from the Machine (1984), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - White Columns, Bunnies (1984), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hallwalls, Objectivity (1984), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Museo Rufino Tamayo, Narrative Forms (1984-1985), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Wesleyan University, Wall Installation, 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - P.S. 1, Narratives (1985), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - New Museum, SIGNS (1985), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Everson Museum of Art, Computers and Art (1988), 1986-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Rosa Esman Gallery, The Language of Form, The Form of Language (1988), 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Printed Material, 1962-1990; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2, OV 5
  Printed material includes magazines articles and news clippings regarding Gary Falk's work. Also included are exhibition announcements, a few photocopied source images, event programs, publications from Yale which mention Falk, and a monograph about Falk printed after his death.
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1977-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gary Falk: A Monograph, circa 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Magazines, 1978-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - News Clippings, circa 1978-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Source Images, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Programs, 1962; 1989; circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Yale Publications, 1971; 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Oversize Poster, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5)
- Photographs, circa 1955-1990s; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 2-4
  Found here are portraits of Gary Falk, personal color snapshots of Falk with friends, photographs of his apartment, and photographs and slides of works of art. Also found are many travel photographs and snapshots of his time as a visiting artist in Cummington, Massachusetts, and black and white photographs taken by Falk.
  - Gary Falk, circa 1955-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Yale Summer School Group Portrait, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cummington, Massachusetts, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Montauk, New York, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mexico, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Loft Apartment, 1986; 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Polaroids, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs and Negatives of Artwork, 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Slides of Gary Falk and Artwork, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs Taken by Gary Falk, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
  - Negatives of Photographs Taken by Gary Falk, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Artwork, 1958-1980s; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 3, OVs 5-7
  Found here are pencil drawings, collages, and two sketchbooks belonging to Gary Falk. Included are clock designs in colored pencil on black paper. Many of the pencil drawings and collages have source material from magazines attached. Also found are student and childhood drawings and two works of art on fabric.
  - Clock Designs, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Collage, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Drawings and Collages, circa 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Oversized material housed in OV 5
  - Drawings, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Holiday Cards Designed by Gary Falk, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Print by L. Kerr, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Oversize Drawings and Collages, circa 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5)
  - Oversize Childhood Drawings, 1958-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5)
  - Oversize Student Artwork, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 6)
  - Oversize Artwork on Fabric, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 7)